AIDAN P. THOMPSON


Principal Member of the Technical Staff
Multiscale Science Department
Center for Computing Research
Sandia National Laboratories
http://www.cs.sandia.gov/~athomps/

P.O. Box 5800, Mail Stop 1322‎
Albuquerque, NM 87185-1322‎
Cell: (505) 218-1011‎
	
EXPERTISE
Atomistic Materials Simulation: interatomic potential development, equilibrium and non-equilibrium molecular dynamics, kinetic Monte Carlo, equilibrium Monte Carlo, statistical physics.‎
High-Performance Computing: software development for leadership computing platforms
CURRENT RESEARCH
SNAP (Spectral Neighbor Analysis Potential): Advancing the state-of-the-art of data-driven interatomic potentials for accurate large-scale atomistic simulations of materials. Developing efficient scalable implementations of SNAP for advanced architectures.  Developing Python framework for fitting SNAP potentials to large sets of quantum data.  Generating robust, fast, and accurate potentials for predictive atomistic simulations of complex multiscale materials physics, including phase change kinetics, plastic yielding, and plasma-surface interactions.‎
Materials Chemistry Modeling: Developing and applying massively parallel implementations of reactive force fields to multi-million atom simulations of energetics materials at extreme conditions.  ‎
LAMMPS: Developing LAMMPS since 1997‎
EDUCATION
University of Pennsylvania	Philadelphia, Pennsylvania‎
Ph.D. in Chemical Engineering, September 1994.‎
	Dissertation:  ‎"Structure and Thermodynamics of Polymers in Random Porous Materials." 
‎	Advisor:	Professor Eduardo D. Glandt
M.S.E. in Chemical Engineering, May, 1991.‎
National University of Ireland	Dublin, Ireland
Bachelor's Degree in Chemical Engineering, May, 1986.‎
	Graduated with First Class Honours.
PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE
Sandia National Laboratories (Center for Computing Research)	Albuquerque, New Mexico	
	Technical Staff	3/1999 - Present
	Post-doctoral Fellow	6/1997 - 2/1999

PUBLICATIONS (h-index 27)‎

Y. Zuo, C. Chen, X. Li, Z. Deng, Y. Chen, J. Behler, G. Csányi, A. V. Shapeev, A. P. Thompson, M. A. Wood, and S. P. Ong "A performance and cost assessment of machine learning interatomic potentials" J. Phys. Chem. A, 124 731 (2020).‎
M. A. Wood, M. A. Cusentino, B. D. Wirth, and A. P. Thompson, "Data-driven material models for atomistic simulation" Phys. Rev. B, 99 184305 (2019).‎
J. M. D. Lane , K. Leung, A. P. Thompson, and M. E Cuneo, "Water desorption from rapidly-heated metal oxide surfaces-first principles, molecular dynamics, and the Temkin isotherm" J. Phys.: Condens. Matter, 30 465002 (2018).‎
J. Tranchida, S. J. Plimpton, P. Thibaudeau, and A. P. Thompson, "Massively parallel symplectic algorithm for coupled magnetic spin dynamics and molecular dynamics" J. Comp. Phys., 148 241721 (2018).‎
M. A. Wood, and A. P. Thompson, "Extending the accuracy of the SNAP interatomic potential form" J. Chem. Phys., 148 241721 (2018).‎
M. A. Wood, D. E. Kittell, C. D. Yarrington, and A. P. Thompson, "Multiscale modeling of shock wave localization in porous energetic material" Phys. Rev. B, 97 014109 (2017).‎
T.-R. Shan, R. R. Wixom, and A. P. Thompson, "Micron-scale Reactive Atomistic Simulations of Void Collapse and Hotspot Growth in PETN" Proceedings 15th International Detonation Symposium, ONR-43-280-15 962 (2015).‎
J. M. D. Lane, A. P. Thompson, and T. J. Vogler, "Enhanced densification, strength and molecular mechanisms in shock compressed porous silicon" Shocked Compression of Condensed Matter, AIP Conf. Proc. 1793 120010 (2017).‎
T.-R. Shan, R. R. Wixom, and A. P. Thompson, "Nanoscale Void-Enhanced Initiation in Hexanitrostilbene" Proceedings 15th International Detonation Symposium, ONR-43-280-15 878 (2015).‎
T. R. Shan, R. R. Wixom, and A. P. Thompson, "Extended asymmetric hot region formation due to shockwave interactions following void collapse in shocked high explosive" Phys. Rev. B, 94 054308 (2016).‎
A. P. Thompson , L.P. Swiler, C.R. Trott, S.M. Foiles, G.J. Tucker, " SNAP: Automated generation of quantum-accurate interatomic potentials" J. Comp. Phys., 285 316 (2015).‎
C.R. Trott, S.D. Hammond, A. P. Thompson, "SNAP: Strong scaling high fidelity molecular dynamics simulations on leadership-class computing platforms" Supercomputing, (Lecture Notes in Computer Science), 8488 19 (2014).‎
J.M.D. Lane, A. P. Thompson, and T.J. Vogler, "Enhanced densification under shock compression in porous silicon" Phys. Rev. B, 90 134311 (2014).‎
S. Levy, K. B. Ferreira, P. G. Bridges A. P. Thompson, and C. R. Trott, "Evaluating the Feasibility of Using Memory Content Similarity to Improve System Resilience" International Journal of High Performance Computing, 28 11 (2014).‎
T. Shan, and A. P. Thompson, "Shock-induced hotspot formation and chemical reaction initiation in PETN containing a spherical void" Journal of Physics: Conference Series, 500 172009 (2014).‎
A. P. Thompson, and T. Shan, "Reactive atomistic simulations of shock-induced initiation processes in mixtures of ammonium nitrate and fuel oil" Journal of Physics: Conference Series, 500 052046 (2014).‎
T. Shan, A. C. T. van Duin, A. P. Thompson , "Development of a ReaxFF Reactive Force Field for Ammonium Nitrate and Application to Shock Hugoniots, " J. Phys. Chem. A, 118 000 (2014).‎
R. J. Bondi, M. P. Desjarlais, A. P. Thompson , G. L. Brennecka, and M. J. Marinella, "Electrical conductivity in oxygen-deficient phases of tantalum pentoxide from first-principles calculations" J. Appl. Phys., 114 203701 (2013).‎
S. Root, T. A. Haill, J. M. D. Lane, A. P. Thompson , G. S. Grest, D. G. Schroen, and T. R. Mattsson, "Shock compression of hydrocarbon foam to 200 GPa: Experiments, atomistic simulations, and mesoscale hydrodynamic modeling" J. Appl. Phys., 114 103502 (2013).‎
T.-R. Shan, R. R. Wixom, A. E. Mattsson, and A. P. Thompson , "Atomistic Simulation of Orientation Dependence in Shock-Induced Initiation of Pentaerythritol Tetranitrate" J. Phys. Chem. B, 117 928 (2013).‎
S. J. Plimpton, and A. P. Thompson , "Computational aspects of many-body potentials" Mat. Res. Soc. Bulletin, 37 513 (2012).
P. L. Theofanis, A. Jaramillo-Botero, W. A. Goddard III, T. R. Mattsson, and A. P. Thompson , "Electron dynamics of shocked polyethylene crystal" Phys. Rev. B, 85 094109 (2012).
J. M. D. Lane, G. S. Grest, A. P. Thompson, K. R. Cochrane, M. Desjarlais, and T. R. Mattsson, "Shock compression of dense polymer and foam systems using molecular dynamics and DFT" Shocked Compression of Condensed Matter, AIP Conf. Proc. 1426 1435 (2012).
A. P. Thompson, J. M. D. Lane, and M. Desjarlais, "Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Dynamic Response of Beryllium" Shocked Compression of Condensed Matter, AIP Conf. Proc. 1426 1311 (2012).‎
S. Jayaraman, A. P. Thompson, and O. A. von Lilienfeld, "Molten salt eutectics from atomistic simulations" Phys. Rev. E, 84 030201 (2011).‎
H. Asegun, G. Chen, S. J. Plimpton, and A. P. Thompson, "1D-to-3D transition of phonon heat conduction in polyethylene using molecular dynamics simulations" Phys. Rev. B, 82 144308 (2010).‎
S. V. Zybin, W. A. Goddard, P. Xu, A. C. T. van Duin, and A. P. Thompson, "Physical mechanism of anisotropic sensitivity in pentaerythritol tetranitrate from compressive-shear reaction dynamics simulations" Appl. Phys. Lett., 96 081918 (2010).
S. Martin, A. P. Thompson, E. A. Coutsias, and J. P. Watson, "Topology of cyclo-octane energy landscape " J. Chem. Phys., 132 234115 (2010).
W. M. Brown, A. P. Thompson, and P. A. Schultz, "Efficient Hybrid Evolutionary Optimization of Interatomic Potential Models" J. Chem. Phys., 132 024108 (2010).
T. R. Mattsson, J. M. D. Lane, K. R. Cochrane, M. P. Desjarlais, A. P. Thompson, F. Pierce, and G. S. Grest, "First-Principles and Classical Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Shocked Polymers " Phys. Rev. B, 81 054103 (2010).
S. Jayaraman, A. P. Thompson, O. A. von Lilienfeld, and E. J. Maginn, "Molecular simulation of the thermal and transport properties of three alkali nitrate salts" Ind. & Eng. Chem. Res., 49 559 (2010).
A. P. Thompson, S. J. Plimpton, and W. Mattson, "General Formulation of Pressure and Stress Tensor for Arbitrary Many-body Interaction Potentials under Periodic Boundary Conditions" J. Chem. Phys., 131 154107 (2009).
J. Budzien, A. P. Thompson, and S. V. Zybin, "Reactive Molecular Dynamics Simulations of Shock Through a Single Crystal of Pentaerythritol Tetranitrate" J. Phys. Chem. B, 113 13142 (2009).
A. P. Thompson, J. M. D. Lane , M. P. Desjarlais, and M. I. Baskes, "Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Dynamic Response of Beryllium" Shocked Compression of Condensed Matter, AIP CP1195 833 (2009).
J. M. D. Lane, and A. P. Thompson, "Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Shock-Induced Phase Transformation in Germanium" Shocked Compression of Condensed Matter, AIP CP1195 1157 (2009).
A. A. Selezenev, A. Yu. Aleynikov, N. S. Ganchuk, P.V. Ermakov, S. N. Ganchuk, J. B. Aidun, and A. P. Thompson, "Shock Compression Calculation of RDX and PETN Molecular Crystals using Hugoniostat Method" Shocked Compression of Condensed Matter, AIP CP1195 821 (2009).
J. Budzien, D. R. Rottach, J. G. Curro, C. S. Lo, A. P. Thompson, "A New Constitutive Model for the Chemical Aging of Rubber Networks in Deformed States" Macromolecules, 41 9896 (2008)
A. Slepoy, A. P. Thompson, S. J. Plimpton, "A Constant-Time Kinetic Monte Carlo Algorithm for Simulation of Large Biochemical Reaction Networks" J. Chem. Phys., 128 205101 (2008)
A. Slepoy, M. D. Peters, and A. P. Thompson, "Searching for Globally Optimal Functional Forms for Interatomic Potentials Using Genetic Programming with Parallel Tempering" J. Comp. Chem., 28 2465 (2007)‎
J. Quenneville, T. C. Germann, A. P. Thompson, E. M. Kober, "Molecular dynamics studies of thermal induced chemistry in TATB" SCCM 2007, AIP CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS, 955 451-454 (2007).‎
A. H. Edwards, A. C. Pineda, P. A. Schultz, M. G. Martin, A. P. Thompson, H. P. Hjalmarson, C. J. Umrigar, "Electronic structure of intrinsic defects in crystalline germanium telluride" Phys. Rev. B, 73 45210 (2006).‎
A. H. Edwards, A. C. Pineda, P. A. Schultz, M. G. Martin, A. P. Thompson, H. P. Hjalmarson, "Theory of persistent, p-type, metallic conduction in c-GeTe" J. Phys.: Cond. Mat., 17 329-35 (2005)‎
D. Rottach, J. G. Curro, G. S. Grest, and A. P. Thompson, "Effect of Strain History on Stress and Permanent Set in Crosslinking Networks: A Molecular Dynamics Study" Macromolecules, 37 5468 (2004).‎
M. G. Martin, and A. P. Thompson, "Industrial Property Prediction using Towhee and LAMMPS" Fluid Phase Equilibria, 217 105 (2004)
A. P. Thompson, "Non-equilibrium Molecular Dynamics Simulation of Electroosmotic Flow in a Charged Nanopore"  J. Chem. Phys., 119 7503 (2003)‎
M. G. Martin, A. P. Thompson, and T. M. Nenoff, "Effect of Pressure, Membrane Thickness and Placement of Control Volumes on the Flux of Methane through Thin Silicalite Membranes" J. Chem. Phys., 114 7174 (2001)‎
M. Chandross, E. B. Webb, G. S. Grest, M. G. Martin, A. P. Thompson, and M. W. Roth, "Dynamics and Exchange at Gas-Zeolite Interfaces I: Pure Component Butane and Isobutane" J. Phys. Chem. B, 105 5700 (2001).‎
P. S. Rallabandi, A. P. Thompson, D. M. Ford, "A molecular modeling study of entropic and energetic selectivities in air separation with glassy polymers" Macromolecules, 33 3142 (2000)
L. J. D. Frink, A. P. Thompson, and A. G. Salinger, "Applying molecular theory to steady-state diffusing systems" J. Chem. Phys., 112 7564 (2000)
A. P. Thompson, and G. S. Heffelfinger, "Direct Molecular Simulation of Gradient Driven Diffusion of Large Molecules using Constant Pressure" J. Chem. Phys., 110 10693 (1999)
A. P. Thompson, , D. M. Ford, and G. S. Heffelfinger, "Direct Molecular Simulation of Gradient Driven Diffusion" J. Chem. Phys., 109 6406 (1998).‎
D. M. Ford, A. P. Thompson, and E. D. Glandt, "Thermodynamics of Fluids in Random Microporous Materials from Scaled Particle Theory" J. Chem. Phys., 103 1099 (1995).‎
A. P. Thompson, , and E. D. Glandt, "Polymers in Random Porous Materials: Structure, Thermodynamics and Concentration Effects" Macromolecules, 29 4314 (1996).
A. P. Thompson, and E. D. Glandt, "Adsorption of Polymeric Fluids in Microporous Materials. I. Ideal Freely-jointed Chains" J. Chem. Phys., 99 8325 (1993).
A. P. Thompson, D. S. Corti, A. L. Myers, and E. D. Glandt, "Irreversible Adsorption in Porous Materials" Fundamentals of Adsorption: Proc. IVth Int. Conf. on Fundamentals of Adsorption, p. 397 (Kodansha, 1993).
A. P. Thompson, and E. D. Glandt, "Low Coverage Kinetics of Correlated Sequential Adsorption" Phys. Rev. A, 46 4639 (1992).
A. P. Thompson, and E. D. Glandt, "The Length of Intersection and the Number of Cusps in Assemblies of Interpenetrating Spheres" J. Chem. Phys., 97 1932 (1992).‎
A. P. Thompson, and E. D. Glandt, "Random Sequential Adsorption in Porous Solids" J. Colloid Interface Sci., 146 63 (1991).‎


INVITED TALKS

‎"Predictive Atomistic Simulations of Materials using SNAP Data-Driven Potentials," American Chemical Society, Philadelphia, April (2020)‎
‎"Prediction of Materials Properties using SNAP Machine-Learned Interatomic Potentials," Artificial Intelligence for Robust Engineering & Science, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Tennessee, January (2020)‎
‎"Molecular Dynamics Simulation: Engine of Discovery or Bridge to Nowhere?" Computer Science, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, August (2019)‎
‎"Predictive Atomistic Simulations of Materials using SNAP Data-Driven Potentials," Materials Science Division, Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory, February (2019)‎
‎"Molecular Dynamics Simulation: Engine of Discovery or Bridge to Nowhere?" Information Science and Technology Institute, Los Alamos National Laboratory, June (2019)‎
‎"Predictive Atomistic Simulations of Materials using SNAP Data-Driven Potentials," American Physical Society, Boston, March (2019)‎
‎"Molecular Dynamics Simulation: Engine of Discovery or Bridge to Nowhere?" Plenary Talk, 21st Biennial Conference of the APS Topical Group on Shock Compression of Condensed Matter, Portland, June (2019)‎
‎"Predictive Atomistic Simulations of Materials using SNAP Machine-Learning Interatomic Potentials," Machine Learning for Computational Fluid and Solid Dynamics conference, Center for Non-Linear Studies, Los Alamos National Laboratory, New Mexico, February (2019)‎
‎ "Molecular Dynamics Simulation:  Engine of Discovery or Bridge to Nowhere?" Physics, University of South Florida, Tampa, September (2018)‎
‎"Molecular Dynamics Simulation:  Engine of Discovery or Bridge to Nowhere?" Chemistry, University of Missouri, Columbia, September (2018)‎
‎"Automated Generation of High-Accuracy Interatomic Potentials Using Quantum Data," Artificial Intelligence for Materials Science (AIMS) workshop, NIST, Gaithersburg, August (2018)‎
‎"Automated Generation of High-Accuracy Interatomic Potentials Using Quantum Data," SIAM Conference on Mathematical Aspects of Materials Science, July (2018)‎
‎"Atomistic Materials Simulation Using Quantum-Accurate Interatomic Potentials," Machine Learning at Interfaces workshop, CECAM-EPFL, Switzerland, June (2018)‎
‎"Automated Generation of High-Accuracy Interatomic Potentials using Quantum Data," TMS Annual Meeting, Phoenix, March (2018)‎
Machine Learning and Data Science in Materials Modeling, Imaging and Applications, Argonne National Laboratory, May (2017)‎
‎"LAMMPS: A general open-source framework for particle-based simulation of materials on multiple scales," CECAM Workshop on Multiscale Simulation, University College Dublin, Ireland, September (2016)‎
‎"Predictive Atomistic Simulations of Materials Using LAMMPS," Tyndall Institute, University College Cork, Ireland, September (2016)‎
‎"Atomistic Materials Simulation Using Quantum-Accurate Interatomic Potentials," Machine Learning for Many-Particle Systems, Institute for Pure & Applied Mathematics, UCLA, February (2015)‎
‎"Large-Scale Atomistic Materials Simulation Using Quantum-Accurate Interatomic Potentials," Society of Engineering Science Technical Meeting, Purdue University, Indiana, October (2014)‎
‎"Large-Scale Atomistic Materials Simulation Using Quantum-Accurate Interatomic Potentials," MRS Spring Meeting, San Francisco, March (2014)‎
‎"Large-Scale Reactive Atomistic Simulation of Shock-induced Initiation  Processes in Energetic Materials,"  18th Biennial Conference of the APS Topical Group on Shock Compression of Condensed Matter, Seattle, July (2013)‎
‎"Large-Scale Atomistic Materials Modeling Using Quantum-Accurate Interatomic Potentials," Chemical Engineering, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, September (2013)‎
‎"Large-scale reactive atomistic simulation of shock-induced initiation processes energetic materials," American Chemical Society, Indianapolis, September (2013)‎
‎"LAMMPS: Overview, Timescale Acceleration Methods, and Advanced Interatomic Potentials," Center For Materials Simulation, Caltech, Pasadena, June (2011)
"Large Scale Molecular Dynamics Simulation Using Reactive Interatomic Potentials in LAMMPS, " Next Generation Force Fields for Nanoscience workshop, Center for Nanophase Materials Sciences, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Tennessee, September (2010)‎

POST-DOCTORAL MENTORSHIP

Josh Rackers (Sandia Truman Fellow, 2019-present)‎
Julien Tranchida (Sandia post-doc, 2017-2019), converted to Sandia technical staff
Mitch Wood (Sandia post-doc, 2016-2018), converted to Sandia technical staff
Tzu-Ray Shan (Sandia post-doc, 2011-2015), Director of Support, Materials Design, Inc., San Diego‎
Sai Jayaraman (Sandia post-doc, 2009-2012), Senior Research Investigator, Bristol-Myers Squibb, New Jersey‎
Joanne Budzien (Sandia post-doc, 2008-2010), X Computational Physics Division, Los Alamos National Laboratory

STUDENT MENTORSHIP

Jon Willman (U. South Florida, doctoral committee, 2019-present) ‎
Ashley Williams (U. South Florida, doctoral committee, 2019-present) ‎
Elizabeth Decolvenaere (UC Santa Barbara, graduate student intern, 2016), Researcher, D. E. Shaw Research
Tzu-Ray Shan (U. of Florida, graduate student intern, 2012), Director of Support, Materials Design, Inc., San Diego‎
Metin Aktulga (Purdue, graduate student intern, 2009), Assistant Professor, Computer Science, Michigan State University
Hansohl Cho (MIT, graduate student intern, 2008), Assistant Professor of Aeronautics, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology

PROFESSIONAL SERVICE

Reviewer for scientific journals: Physical Review, Journal of Chemical Physics, Journal of Physical Chemistry, Science Advances, Scienctific Reports, npj Computational Materials, Computational Materials Science, Modelling and Simulation in Materials Science and Engineering, Journal of Energetic Materials, Journal of Computational Chemistry, Journal of Chemical Theory and Computation
Reviewer for Research Programs: DOE Basic Energy Science, DOD Multidisciplinary University Research Initiative, Los Alamos National Laboratory LDRD, Sandia National Laboratories LDRD
Session chair, American Physical Society, Denver, March (2020)‎
Review Panel, INCITE Program, DOE Leadership Computing, September (2019)‎
Workshop Chair, LAMMPS Workshop and Symposium, Albuquerque, August (2019)‎
Session chair, 21st Biennial Conference of the APS Topical Group on Shock Compression of Condensed Matter, June (2019)‎
Minisymposium chair, SIAM Conference on Mathematical Aspects of Materials Science(MS18), July 2018
Organizing Committee, LAMMPS Workshop and Symposium, Albuquerque, August (2017)‎
Topic Leader, NSF Workshop on Materials Data, June (2015)‎
Organizing Committee, LAMMPS Workshop and Symposium, Albuquerque, August (2015)‎
Session chair, MRS Spring Meeting, San Francisco, March (2014)‎
Advisory Board, NSF-funded Knowledgebase of Interatomic Potentials (KIM), 2014-present
Organizing Committee, LAMMPS Workshop and Symposium, Albuquerque, August (2013)‎
Organizing Committee, LAMMPS Workshop and Symposium, Albuquerque, August (2011)‎
Organizing Committee, LAMMPS Workshop, Albuquerque, February (2010)‎

AIDAN P. THOMPSON
‎(continued)‎
	

AIDAN P. THOMPSON
‎(continued)‎
	

AIDAN P. THOMPSON
‎(continued)‎
	

